你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院的另一个视频
welcome to another video in the pwn college
内存错误模块
memory  error module
我是Yan。今天我们要讨论的是栈金丝雀
I'm Yan. today we're talking about stack canaries
我们将讲解针对内存破坏漏洞的保护机制
so we're rolling into the mitigations against memory corruption vulnerabilities
栈金丝雀是我们要讲的第一个
um and stack canaries is the 1st one we'll talk about
我说的确实是金丝雀
I say canaries right
栈金丝雀是以金丝雀这种鸟来命名的
stack canaries are very much named after an actual canary
或者说是以过去金矿里的金丝雀的概念命名的
or the concept of canaries in a gold mine back in the olden days
当时还没有先进的技术可以检测空气中的有毒气体
before advanced technology that could detect gases and poisonous gases in the air
矿工们会带一只金丝雀进矿井
miners would bring a canary with them to into the mine
因为金丝雀更容易受到毒气的影响
because canaries are more susceptible to poison gases and
如果他们发现金丝雀突然死了
if they saw that their canary was dead all of a sudden
那他们就得离开矿井
then they need to get out of the mine
因为他们很可能就是下一个
because likely they would be next
这就是金丝雀的概念
all right so that's kind of the concept of a canary and
1998年，该概念专门针对内存损坏漏洞提出
in 1998 this concept was developed for memory corruption vulnerability specifically
原理是用一个数字金丝雀，它会在糟糕的事情发生之前被杀死
the idea was that using a digital canary that would get killed before anything else bad happened
借此你可以保护栈
you could protect the stack
这个概念是由一组来自
this concept was created by a group of researchers from
俄勒冈科学与技术研究生院的研究人员提出的
the Oregon Graduate Institute of Science & Technology
并于1998年在USENIX安全上发布
and published in 1998 at USENIX security
至今仍是学术工作的顶级网络安全所之一
still one of the top cyber security venues for academic work to this day
提出这个概念的人们后来成立了IMMUNIX
and it was created by a group people that went on to found immunix
IMMUNIX公司
which was a company that
利用如StackGuard之类的东西建立了些坚固的Linux系统，
built these sort of very hardened Linux systems  that utilized stuff like StackGuard
后来他们又发明了app armor
and  later on they went on to invent for example app armor
app armor 现在还在用
which is used to this day
当然stackguard 现在也还在用
along with stack guard of course
但应用app armor是专门用来保护
but app armor is specifically used to protect
例如
for example
Docker容器等等
docker containers and so on
他们是非常有影响力的一群人
so very impactful group of people
他们还和一个我十分关注的话题有关
they also in a topic near and dear to my heart
他们参加了2003年的defcon CTF比赛
competed in defcon CTF in the year 2003
我可能在这门课上讲过defcon CTF比赛
I probably talked about defcon CTF in this course
它算是黑客届的奥林匹克
it's essentially a kind of an Olympic of hacking
来自世界各地的顶尖团队都来这里，试图攻击对方
the top groups from all over the world come and try to hack each other
2003年Immunix Linux
and one year in 2003 immunix Linux
由这些研究人员创立的公司
the company founded by these researchers
也在其中
was among them
这张截图是周六拍的
this screenshot was taken on Saturday
当时他们处于领先地位
when they were in the lead
这是2003年举办的第11届Defcon比赛
this is defcon the 11 in 2003
我们录这段视频的17年前
17 years ago as we were recording this
我记得那一年Anomaly队最终赢了
and I believe that year team anomaly ended up winning
周六到周日比赛结束之间一定很激烈
so something radical happened between Saturday and Sunday when the competition ends
Immunix失去了领先优势
and the Immunix lost their lead
这年也是我母校的黑客团队第一年
this also the 1st year where teams from hackers from my graduate institution Alma mater
我毕业与加州大学圣巴巴拉分校
where I did my graduate work UC Santa Barbara
参加比赛，团队名叫WMD
competed under this name WMD
我记得两年后他们
and I think two years later they would
两年还是四年后，他们获得了第一
two years or four years later they would go on to win
我现在有点记不清了
I'm a little discombobulator  now
但这只是历史的一个片段
but it's kind of a snapshot in history and
这些黑客创造了我们今天要讨论的技术
these competitive hackers were creating technology that we'll talk about today
这仍然用于保护栈远离内存错误的影响
that is still used to protect the stack against memory errors
那么什么是栈金丝雀呢
all right so what are stack canaries
栈金丝雀非常简单
stack canaries are pretty simple
栈金丝雀的目标是防止缓冲区溢出
stack canaries are targeted to protect against buffer overflows
我们在本模块中讨论了缓冲区溢出
the buffer overflows that we've been looking at so far in this module
缓冲区溢出这里指栈上的溢出
buffer overflows which are overflows on the stack
覆盖返回地址或者其他变量等等
and overflow the return address or other variables or something along these lines
金丝雀是怎么工作的
how does a canary work
它很简单，在函数序言中
it's fairly straightforward and In a function prologue
你取一个随机值，然后把它写到栈帧的末尾
you take a random value and you write it to the end of the stack frame
就在你能识别的所有缓冲区后面
right after either all of the buffers as you can identify them
在他们的右边
to the right of them
或者在返回地址左边
or right to the left of the return address
然后保存基指针
and saved a base pointer
然后在函数结尾
and then in the function epilogue
您要确保这个值仍然是完整的
you make sure that this value is still intact
如果金丝雀被杀了——有溢出破坏了它
if the canary's been killed if an overflow clobbered it
然后你只需杀死整个程序
then you simply kill the whole program
有趣的是
now the interesting thing
金丝雀值是随机的
is the canary value is random
因此，攻击者不知道金丝雀的值是多少
so an attacker overflowing the entire buffer won't know what the value of the canary is
否则
otherwise
它们可以用完全相同的值覆盖金丝雀
they could overflow with the exact same value
不改变它
and not change it
但是他们不知道这个值
but they don't know that value
所以他们的溢出只会导致程序崩溃
so they have to overflow with something leading to a crash
让我展示给你看，不叭叭了
let me show you rather than keep babbling
ops
差点剧透了
that's looking ahead a little
我们有个缓冲区溢出的例子
so we have our buffer overflow
这是之前视频的例子
that's the example from previous video
这是您可以得到的最简单的溢出
this is as simple overflow as you can get
缓冲区很小，读取量很大
there's a small buffer and a big read
好了，我们来编译一下
alright let's compile it
之前我们编译时使用了这个
before we compile it with this
-fno-stack-protector选项
dashf no stack protector option
现在要玩真的了
now the gloves are off
我们开启栈保护器
let's have the stack protector
编译一下
here we compiled it
有一个工具叫做checksec
there's a utility called checksec
我在视频检查时用过几次
that I've used several times on video checksec
如果你正确使用checksec
checksec if you use it properly
它可以检查文件的安全属性并
will check the security properties of a file and and
告诉你它们是什么
tell you what they are
在这里你可以看到栈金丝雀
in here you can see now this stack canaries
该文件开启了栈金丝雀
this file has stack canaries
已经发现了栈金丝雀
stack canaries have been found
让我们来看看这意味着什么
let's take a look at what this means
嗯
um
我们反汇编一下它
so let's uh disassemble it
滑倒上面，看看main函数
and scroll up and look at the main function
好
all right
main函数里多了些东西
the main function has a couple of additions
在这里有一个很明显的
one that you can kind of see right away is right here
堆栈检查失败 __stack_chk_fail
this stack check fail
结果是
and what happens is
我们从缓冲区的一个地方（rbp-0x8）读入
we read from a place on the buffer
就在栈帧的某个位置之前
right before a place on the stack frame
在栈帧的最右边
at the very right hand side of the stack frame
rbp指向位置的左边
immediately to the left  of where the frame pointer is pointing to
rbp指向的位置保存着主调函数栈帧指针（上一个rbp）
which is where the saved frame pointer of the caller function has been written to
从那里读入一个值到rcx中
we read a value that's there into RCX.
拿它和存在全局内存中的一个值 异或
xor it against a value stored globally in memory
这是一种有点古老的访问内存的方法
this is a bit of an archaic way to access memory
就是所谓的段式（段式、页式、段页式）
using what was called segmentation
这说来话长
it's a whole history lesson
简单讲是在内存的某个隐秘角落
but basically this is somewhere in memory in a secret spot
由这个FS寄存器索引，它不能直接访问
indexed by this FS register that can't actually be access direct
只能将其用于内存查找
but you can only use it for memory lookup
所以用它隐藏金丝雀值很好
so it's great for this to hide this canary value
不管这个FS寄存器指向内存那里
anyways at whatever memories pointed to by this FS register
fs值加上0x28的位置，有一个秘密的金丝雀值
plus hex 28 there's a secret canary value
它与RCX异或
it xor with an rcx
如果它们相等
and if they're equal
然后执行main + 5A
then the execution goes to main plus 5A
就是1203这里，正常的函数尾声
which is this 1203 which is the normal epilogue
如果它们不相等，我们就会陷入这个
if they're not equal we fall through to this
栈检查失败
stack check fail
让我给你们看看这是什么样子的
let me show you what this looks like
发生了栈溢出，boom，栈检查失败
this is an overflow boom this is stack check fail
检测到了栈溢出，中止了程序
so stack smashing detected terminates the program
那么这个值是从哪里来的呢
so where did this value come from
值是在这里写的，在开启栈金丝雀后的扩展序言中
this value was written over here in the extended prologue with the stack canaries
从rax里加载的
it came from rax
rax的值来自和检测时同一个秘密地点
rax came from originally the same secret location
很直接
pretty straightforward
基本上就是当程序启动
basically the program starts up
有一个秘密位置初始化一个随机值
there's a secret location that's initialized with a random value
该随机值被移动到栈中
that random value is moved to the stack
如果它在栈上被溢出破坏
then if it is then overflowed on the stack
然后随机值
then the random value
然后对该值的检查将失败
then the check for that value will fail
程序将中止执行
and we will abort execution
让我们快速地在GDB里看一下
let's take a look in GDB real quick
好
okay
让我们在main下断点
let's break in main
运行
run
这是接下来的五条指令
okay here's the next five instructions
让我们向前一步
so let's step forward
好了，现在我们要从这个秘密地点读入值到rax
okay so here we're about to read from this secret location to rax
这是现在的rax
so here's rax right now
里面有个地址。这是现在的样子
some address that was in there. here is what it is now
注意，栈金丝雀是一堆以0结尾的东西
note the stack canary is a bunch of stuff ending in zero
当然这是小端序
of course this is little endian
所以它实际上是以一个Null字节开始的
so it actually starts with an Null byte
这很重要
this becomes important in the future
当然了
and then of course
这时它被写入栈
here is where it got written to the stack
让我们看一下栈
let's take a look at the stack
这是现在栈上的东西
so here's what's on the stack right now
一堆乱七八糟的数据，这是我们的金丝雀
a bunch of messy data and here's our canary
在栈中相当深
while fairly deep in the stack
如果我们继续下去，最后我们会执行这个读取
um if we just keep going eventually we do this read
然后当我们用一堆a来覆盖金丝雀
and then when we overflow that canary with a bunch of A's
让我们再看看我们的栈
let's take a look at our stack again
都是a。金丝雀不见了
it's all As. the canary is gone
原来就在这里
it was right here
我们往上翻，就在这里
we scroll up right there
现在它消失了
and now it is gone
我们继续
let's keep going
在这里
here
我们把值
we move the value
金丝雀本该完好无损
out of the stack where the canary should be intact
加载到rcx
into  rcx
这是现在的RCX
here's rcx now
这是个坏消息
that's bad news
这本应该是金丝雀，但我们溢出了它
that should be the canary right but we overflowed it
然后拿它和秘密地点加载的RCX异或
and xor RCX from this secret location
结果肯定不是零
and that is very much not zero
如果两个值是相等的就该是0
it would have been zero if it was equal of course and
现在 je 要检查零标志位
now jump equals of course checks for the zero flag
零标志未设置
the zero flag is not set
所以会调用 stack_chk_fail
so we call stack check fail
并在打印此错误消息后退出程序
and be aboard out of the program after printing this error message
这就是栈金丝雀的工作原理
that is how a stack canary works
超级有趣的东西
super interesting stuff
好的，那么
okay so um
栈金丝雀有效吗
Are stack canaries effective
事实证明是的
um it turns out that yes
栈金丝雀非常有效
stack canaries are extremely effective
等一下，我把这张幻灯片修复一下
um one SEC let me fix this slide real quick
好了
all right there we go
现在你可以看到完整张幻灯片了
that's better now you can read the whole slide
正如我提到的
so as I mentioned
栈金丝雀非常有效
stack canaries are very effective
有一些保护措施
there are certain mitigations
要绕过他们
that to bypass them
你真的需要一个额外的漏洞
you would you really require an entire additional vulnerability
或者非常幸运
or to get extremely lucky
栈金丝雀就是这样一种保护措施
stack canaries are such a mitigation
要绕过栈金丝雀
to bypass a stack canaries
你要么直接用另一个漏洞泄露它
you either need to straight up leak it with another vulnerability
这绝对不容易
that's definitely not easy
因为这需要一个额外的漏洞
that requires an entirely additional vulnerability
也许你可以用
maybe you can use
你用来溢出覆盖的漏洞
the same vulnerability that you use to do the overwrite
用一种稍微不同的方式来读取
in a slightly different way to do the read
但这要视情况而定
but it's very situational
在某些情况下，你可以暴力破解金丝雀值
in certain cases you can brute force a canary
如果漏洞程序会fork子进程
if you have a forking process
许多许多网络服务都会fork子进程
many many many network services are forking processes
有趣的是
and interestingly enough
如果你用的是安卓手机，你手机上的每一个进程
every process on your phone if you have an android phone
都是从同一个进程中fork出来的（zygote进程）
forks off of one parent process
金丝雀只被初始化
the canary is only initialized
秘密内存仅在进程启动时使用随机数据进行初始化
that secret  memory region is initialized with random data only at startup of the process
它不会在每次函数执行时都重新随机化
it is not re randomized on every function execution or anything like that
只是在进程启动时才随机化
just at every startup time of the process it's randomized
如果你用的是安卓手机
so if you have an android phone
在android手机上，每个进程都从一个父进程fork出来
and every process forks off of a parent process on an android phone
这个父进程叫做受精卵（zygote）
that parent processor called the zygote
你手机上每一个进程中的每一个金丝雀都是一样的
every single canary in every single process on your phone is the same
如果你泄露了一个，你就全都知道了
if you leak one you know them all
但这是一种独特的情况
but that's kind of a unique situation
我快速的讲一下
I'm going to very quickly jump in
并向您展示网络服务中常用的fork大概是什么样的
and show you how a network forking service works
当然，这个示例服务并没真正使用网络
of course this service isn't a network forking service
我在这个forker.c 中实现了它
I implemented it in this forker. c
forker程序有一个缓冲区
and forker has a buffer
它会不断fork子进程
and it'll continuously fork
如果是父进程
if it's the parent
它会等待子进程
it'll wait on the child process
如果是子进程
if it's the child
它会读入过多的东西到缓冲区
it will read way too much into the buffer
导致溢出
and overflow itself
编译时会开启金丝雀
and we're gonna compile this with canaries
手套脱了（直面困难）
gloves are off
好吧
okay
Forker已编译
forker is compiled
我们会执行并展示
and we're going to run it and show
我们如何利用父进程fork子进程这一情况
how we can actually use the fact that the parent forks a child off
这意味着子进程是一个独立的进程
which means the child is an independent process
如果它死了
if it dies
没问题，父进程会fork一个新的
no problem the parent will just spawn a new one
当然，我们会在pwntools中展示
and we're going to show in pwntools of course
我们怎样才能
how we can
抱歉，这是前面的
sorry that's looking ahead
我们可以怎样玩弄它
how we can mess with it
PWN调试
so pwn debug
pwn.gdb.debug
当然，在GDB中打开了我们的进程
opens up our process in GDB of course
这样我们可以在main上打断点，而不是在我身上
this is so that we can break at main not at me
我们到了main
here we are at Main
我只想知道金丝雀的值
I just want to get the value of that canary
现在我们要把它读给rax
so here we're about to read it into rax
这里写入RBP - 0x8
here we are writing into RBP minus 0x8
这是金丝雀值
here's the canary value
让我们做一件事
let's do one thing let's
这是它小端序的样子
this is it in little endian
这是它大端序的样子
this is it in big endian
所以它从第一个字节是零
so it starts at the 1st byte is zero
52 Ed等等
52 ed and so on
让我告诉你发生了什么
let me show you what happens
因为孩子会fork
because the child forks
我们可以不断地与它互动
we can continually interact with it
当然可以，如果我们写
we can of course if we do r.write
我们写入128个A
and we write an A byte 128 times
然后我们执行r.read
and then we do r.read
然后打印出来
and print that
稍等，gdb这里继续一下
hold on me to continue here
然后我们看到检测到栈破坏
then we see stack smashing detected terminating
128字节当然会破坏栈
so 128 of course smashes the stack
好的是我们可以反复做这件事
the nice things we can do this repeatedly
因为这个父进程不断地fork子进程
because the process continually forks
父进程会生成新的子进程来处理我们的输入
the parent is spinning up new children to handle our input
现在我们可以开始利用这个了
so now we can start messing with this
所以好的，16字节太多了吗
so let's say okay  is 16 too much
不，还没覆盖到金丝雀
no we haven't over it in the canary yet
那32字节呢
what about 32
是的，我们用二分搜索对金丝雀进行覆盖
yes we over the canary we do a binary search
0x18字节呢
what about hex 18
这是，嗯
this is um um
我蒙住了
my mind just one blank
24字节
24 bytes
哦，还不是
oh still not
金丝雀可能
so probably the canary
在这后面8字节
is  the eight bytes after this
假设这里是一个a字节
so let's say a just an a byte here
boom
破坏了金丝雀，覆盖了它
broke the canary overwrote it
坏消息，如果我们用B呢，还是坏消息
bad news what about if we do B  still bad news
但是我们知道
but we know
我们知道金丝雀的第一个字节是多少
we know what the 1st byte of the canary is right
金丝雀的第一个字节是0
the 1st byte of the canary is a 0
这里的这个字节
this byte right here
如果我们在里面写一个0
if we write a 0 into it
当当当当，是因为金丝雀的值没有改变
golden because the canary's value didn't change
金丝雀校验不检查金丝雀是否被覆盖
the canary check doesn't check if the canary was over written
它实际上只检查金丝雀是否变了
it actually checks has the canary been changed
如果它被相同的值覆盖
if it was overwritten with the same value
检查一样通过，我们可以利用这点
it's a pervably happy check and we can use this
逐字节暴力破解
to gradually brute force value after value
让我们从1开始，不是
let's start with one nope
two
不是，我要作弊了，但我不需要作弊
nope I'm gonna cheat but I don't have to cheat
我可以一直数到0x52
I could count all the way up to hex 52
我们又破解了一字节
we got another one
那么第三个字节呢
what about the 3rd byte
不是
not one
不是两
not two
让我们随机猜EB
let's take a random guess EB
不是
nope
我记错了，是ed
I miss from out of the E d
是的
yes
fork令人惊奇的
the amazing thing is in a forking process
不光是暴力破解金丝雀值
this doesn't just apply through the canary
利用它可以逐字节泄露任何数据
it's any data I can leak out bite by byte
fork之前栈的整个状态
the entire state of the stacked before the fork occurred
因为我可以一直查询同一个进程的子进程
because I can keep querying the same children of the same process
一遍又一遍
over and over and over
非常酷
very cool stuff
还有一种方式也是非常情境化的
there's another way that's also very situational that
如果你的堆栈布局得当，你可以绕过金丝雀
you can bypass a canary if your stack is laid out just right
当然，现代编译器会有意地以安全的方式布局堆栈
and modern compilers will intentionally lay out the stack  in the secure way of course
但对于攻击者来说是错误的（不利于成功利用漏洞）
but for an attacker the wrong way
但是如果栈的布局恰到好处
but if the stack is layout just right for example
因为它的数据结构恰巧是这样
because it is a data structure that happens to be like this
你在栈上有一个计数器，利用缓冲区溢出可以溢出覆盖它
and you have an counter on the stack that your buffer overflows into
这个程序本来会从0数到128
so this program will count from 0 to 1 28
然后从那个偏移量读入缓冲区
and read at that offset into the buffer
一次一个字节
one byte at a time
这种情况在复制数据时一般会发生
this happens especially when copying data
相比读数据来说
more than when reading
这只是一个简易版本
this is just a minimized version
当缓冲区溢出时
at some point as you overflowed this buffer
你会开始写I计数器
you'll start writing into the i counter
一旦你开始写I计数器
once you start writing the i counter
你可以直接改变你要写的地方
you can directly change where you're writing
例如，您可以跳过金丝雀直接写返回地址
you can jump to write beyond the canary at the return value for example
你需要非常幸运
this you need to get very lucky
一般来说
generally speaking
运气可没这么眷顾我们
luck does not favor us this much
但还是有办法绕过金丝雀的
but there are ways to get around the canary
要么是视情况的，要么是需要一个新的漏洞来泄露值
there just either situational or require a new vulnerability to leak it out
之后的视频中
and then later videos
我们会研究这个新的漏洞会是
we will actually look into what that new vulnerability might or
这样的漏洞可能是什么样的
what such vulnerabilities might look like
到时见
see you then